hi and welcome back to another tutorial in the
GrandMA 3 tutorial series for beginners this
time it's about sequences or GrandMA 3 sequences
what is a sequence you can think of a sequence as
a container of cues in a sequence you can have
multiple cues you can have only one que but
basically this is where cues live the reason
why you have sequences is that you can record
cues in a sequence and when you do that it's going
to appear here on sequence number one or number
two or whichever one you're working at the cool
thing is you can move them around afterwards so
depending on where you want to use it you can you
can move it you can assign it to a fader you can
assign it to a button that doesn't matter as long
as you have it in your sequence pool it's safe
and you can use it wherever so let's start
by building our first sequence what you do is
you turn on basically some of your moving lights
are some of your dimmers in this case we're doing
it with our vipers we put them in a position we
give them a color we maybe give the magenta it's
easy to see and then we can zoom them in if we
want to and store this in a sequence number one
right now we stored one cue in one sequence a good
thing when you work on lighting in general is to
label everything so let's just label this one to
our master cue list there we go so now we have
our master cue list our master cue list has only
one queue in it but if we need to record any more
cues we need to have a different view because
we can't see what we're doing right now we need
to change it around just a little bit this is a
great view we built it on episode i think it was
episode number two episode number three in
this tutorial series we need to change it
up a little bit just to be sure that we can
work with it that we can see what we're doing
so let's start by deleting the 3d window just
for a second we delete the the beam directory
over here we don't really use it anyway we put our
focus down here and then we move all our colors
down in the bottom maybe we rescale the sequence
sheet just a little bit here or the secret pool
sequence pool sorry then we open up our 3d
window again we scale it all the way down
like this and we move it to the side right here
you can see this little lock up here that's
because we need to change the camera to the front
camera we need to zoom in just a little bit so we
can see what's going on and up here we need to
open the playbacks or the playback the playback
is a representation of the first 10 faders on
your console so if you store something right
here for instance that's the first fader it's
a little bit big right now we have the first
10 faders we only need the first five so we can
see what we're doing so we go into sections here
repress it once or you can right click it
and see how many sections do you want to see
at the same time we close this one down and then
we have our first five faders we can rescale it
like this so we can see what's happening and then
we can open our sequence sheet down here this is
our cue list or our sequence sheet and we stored
a cue before and we have the queue right here with
our information in it so we we have our sequence
the sequence is living in the sequence pool right
here we can't really work with it because
it's not assigned to anything so if we want
to assign it we press alt plus a for the assign
if you have the shortcuts activated over here
we press the master cue list and we assign it to
201 this is the first fader on the console that
gives us a go button right here so now we can go
our cue list the way we want to let's make some
sort of change we have our cue now and we need to
record some other stuff let's say we take all our
vipers again and move them to a different position
let's move them to our roof position like this
we need to once again store it and we store it
on our master cue list and now it asks us a few
questions do you want to override the que
you're in do you want to merge it into the que
do you want to remove some values do you
want to release it or do you want to create
a second cue in this case we want to create a
second queue because we are building a cue list
that contains more than one queue so the first
time you try to store into a sequence that has
only one que in it it's going to ask you if
you want to create a second que if we say yes
it creates que number two but the next time
we try to store into the same cue list it's not
gonna ask us it's just automatically gonna assume
that you want an extra cue so next time it's gonna
automatically create cue number three so let's
clear out here we moved the the moving lights into
a new position when we clear out it goes back
to what it was doing before because we're still
in que number one but if i press the go button
up here it's going to do what we just asked it
to do because we are now in cue number two if
we press go again it goes back to cue number
one and we say okay we can just try it again say
it's very fast when it goes into cue number one
but maybe it's a little too fast so i can say down
here on our fade time if i right click here and i
say i wanted to do it in five seconds please it
changed to five seconds then if i go back to cue
number one like we have here and then now i go
into cue number two we just set a fade time of
five seconds we press go and the change is now
going to be five seconds which is really cool
now we can go back to cue number one and say
okay are we done with cue number one do we
need to add something to it i think we need to
add all our auras in position number two maybe
we need to have them in open white we need to
have a narrow beam and we need to turn them on
like this maybe we need to take them
in the roof position yeah there we go
so to store this in cue number one we just press
store and we push this one queue number one and
it's going to ask you do you want to merge
do you want to remove release or overwrite
i think i would like to merge it into cue number
one so i select that one if i clear out now cue
number one now consists of our vipers as
we did before and now our auras as well
if i press the go button it's going to do the
change for the viper as we did before and the
auras are going to stay in their position because
we didn't give them any other information it's
just going to track the values i'm going to do a
tutorial on tracking in a in a later series here
on a later tutorial because it's a little bit
more complex if you don't know what tracking is
so here we go we have cue number one and cue
number two let's just for the fun of it
record another cue let's say all our auras
again let's just change them to blue and we
once again store it in our master cue list and
now it automatically just created cue number three
the next time we're going to store a queue in
this cue list it's going to be cue number four
but as you can see we are already running out
of room here so a cool little feature you can
do in the GrandMA 3 software is you can go in here
and you can find the font size and you can right
click and set the font size to 10 for instance and
when we go back the font size is a lot smaller so
we can see a lot more of the cue list
and we can even rescale some of this to
to remove some of the things we don't really need
right now this brings some of this stuff like
duration and que time fade time a little bit
closer  to us so we can better work with it
we built our view we played with our ques let's
just store this view so we have it next time we go
down and we press store and we store it up here
in this view pool up here and we say see coins
and that way we can access it next time we still
have our first view as we build in the one of
the first episodes and now we have our sequence
view here when we need to work with our cue lists
working with cues is can be pretty simple but you
can start combining one cue list with another cue
list you can have moving lights like we have
now which are turned on in say magenta like the
vipers are now and then you can have another
cue list who bumps out the color if you want
to do like a festival gig or something like that
so we need to assign it to our faders we need to
have our go buttons we need to have our flash
buttons we need to to assign this room up here and
and to to use the turn knobs and all that stuff
if you want to know more about that you have to
check out the next episode in this tutorial series
on GrandMA 3 programming i hope you enjoyed
this episode if you have any comments or anything
you want to say to me please leave a comment down
in the comment section and i definitely hope to
see you next time if you get any value out of
these videos please consider subscribing to the
channel so you get a notification next time we
upload a video or maybe you could check out some
of our other videos they are linked right here on
the screen right now i hope to see you next time
on the channel and thank you very much bye bye